It, Amanda.
>> Sorry.
Amanda, when I come on before I get started, if you can tell me, Jeff, a heads up, I
apologize for that. No worries. So we're going to get started with the Town of Andover Board of Selectmen special budget meeting for
02/22/2022.
And we're going get started with the Pledge of Allegiance.
I pledge allegiance to the flag
of The United States Of America and to the republic
for which it stands,
one nation, your God, indivisible,
liberty, and justice for all. All right. Thank you very much.
And we're going to move on to public speak.
And so we're going to start with Kathy Palazzi.
Fine. Thank you. Okay.
>> Jarrett, we're going to skip you and come back to you because I believe you're going to
be on the agenda.
Lynette Harlow?
Yes.
>> Public speak, would you like to No, I'm just here to support Jarrett. Okay, you got it. Thank you.
Good.
Diane Greiner?
>> Hello.
I would just like to ask that all the board of selectmen have their video
turned on. I think it's important to be able to see the expressions and see the faces of who we're dealing with.
I think it's important and also polite.
So I think the speakers and the Board of Selecting members should have their video turned on, Diane,
>> thank you very much.
As soon as dinner is over, we'll we'll sit there and get it organized. Thank you. No problem. Yeah. Soon as dinner is over, I will turn my camera on.
You know? And, Scott, thank you for the faces. That really makes me feel good. I I appreciate that. Thank you.
Bill Penn. Ms. Stanley?
Have
>> no public comments. I'm here to support Jarrett Lundberg's
scout proposal.
All right, thank you very much. Thank you. Good day. Zia and Choquette?
I'm all set. Thank you. All right. Joanne Ebert?
>> All set. Thanks. All right. And Michael?
Okay.
Hi,
Michael, go ahead.
>> No, I just joined the meeting. It's off. Sorry. All right.
>> Just got in for public speak. So you got nothing to go. We'll get out with this. But first, before we get started, I want to apologize for last week.
I had screwed up my schedule, and I did not realize we had that meeting. And tonight, I'm gonna apologize in advance because I have a prearranged meeting that I have to attend, so we're gonna get moving.
Let's go. Alright? So, Jarrett,
you are the first person on the agenda for the Eagle Scout project for the transfer station cart program. So if you would like to give us a
rundown of what you're thinking, and we can sit there and
get voting on that. Yes, I made a
>> bill of materials to
basically lay out the
what I'm planning on and what what it'll cost and everything.
If I can share my screen possibly.
Go ahead, Jared.
Can
>> you see it? That's not it. That is definitely
not it.
Looks like a bill of materials. It is. Is it? Yeah. Yep. Yep. Okay. Perfect.
So
yeah. Pretty much it's it's just
the long hinge table as
we were talking about when we were at the transfer station, and then
the
sorting table for glass was one
one side of it angled
to make it easier to sort. And then
four bins to
make it a little bit more organized for the public to
sort their recyclables
and
all the materials that will
be needed.
Yeah.
>> So I'm assuming Jared that you met with Scott and Jeff. Is that accurate?
Yes.
Alright and Scott and Jeff, do you have any
comments on Jared's plan? How many
>> bins
is this gonna be making Jared? Three you said in the beginning?
>> There so it was
four for each of the different kinds of
things that we're recycling,
which is glass,
cans,
small plastic, one liter and two liter.
>> K. So the bin the bins are for the people that are sorting. Right? So it's They're they're kind of for both. So they'll be stationary
>> for
people placing stuff in, and then
they can be moved around
so they can so the people that that are doing cart can
sort into
specific bins so they can be bagged or done with whatever they need to be done with.
>> Right.
So
just go over what your plan is with the material here,
Jared.
>> Yeah, so the plywood would be for the top of the sorting table for the glass
and for the the long hinge table
because
those just need solid surfaces to sort on.
And then
the two by fours are for structural support
for all of the
for all
of the different things that I'm going to be doing.
Yeah. The
>> 4x4 is No, I I listen. I I appreciate you want to go through the whole list, but Scott, if you approve this and Jeff, if you're good with that,
let's, you know, let's let's move this along.
>> Did did Mike Pelosi get a chance to look at this, Jared?
I'm
don't believe so. Well, he was there when
>> we went over it there, but he didn't He was gonna be with you. You went there. Mike, are you there? Yes. Yeah. I'm trying to get into my meeting too. I got a meeting at same time, but I was there. Yes. So are you okay with everything because you are in charge of CART? Yep. I sent a note out to the CART people, and I've only gotten a response from one of them. And I I called Scott and told him that tonight. I think this is gonna be an adjustment as time goes on. Okay. Because the biggest complaint I'm hearing is if we put up these three special bins to help segregate the material right on-site there, the people won't do it. I said, but they'll do it over time.
They won't do a 100% ever.
But whatever they do, 50%, 60%
over time, that's more things they don't have to sort. Got it. Okay.
>> Alright.
So
let's go back to Scott and Jeff. So you two were at this this meeting and you understand what Jared is looking to construct for his Eagle Scout project. Are you guys in favor and all set with what his thought process
is?
>> Jeff Murray? Yes, I understand it. He's also going to remove the
metal fence that was part of the old cart as part of this Yep.
>> All right. Awesome. I make a motion that we accept the
Eagle Scout project as
submitted.
>> Where's
We need to talk to Eric. Mean, he's asking for funds, so we need to find Where's it gonna be paid from?
That's a Board of Finance question.
>> Let's,
Jared, if you can get with me after this meeting,
I will assist you with the funds.
Okay. Alright. Yep.
>> Alright. Thank you.
So Adrian made a motion. Is someone gonna second that? I'll second that.
Okay.
Further discussion?
Alright. All those in favor? Aye.
Aye.
>> Aye.
Okay.
So, five in favor. Jarrett, thank you very much. And Jarrett,
email me later and I'll assist you. I'll get with other people related to this. Alrighty.
>> Thank you so much. Good luck. Thanks, Jarrett. Thank you very much, Jarrett. Yep. We'll see you later. Okay. Thank you.
Alright.
Sorry.
No.
My
agenda went away there.
Next item up is just discussion of the budget.
So Item
>> Adrian, you had a list of items and you saw Eric's list.
>> I did not see Eric's list. Was that sent over today? Yes.
I apologize if this is the first time I've been on a computer today, so.
Okay.
>> Do you need that list?
I have it in front of me. Do you need me to read it?
No, I got it. Hang on.
>> Okay,
so let's go to the list that sits there and says major decisions for tonight's meeting. Yep.
All right.
>> We at previous meetings have discussed salary increases for non
collective bargaining positions.
>> You know? Yeah, I, personally,
I think we already talked about 3%.
I think that should include JTuttle.
Again, when you take a position, if you expect something other than the norm, then you should have negotiated that.
That's my personal take on it.
>> Okay.
Does anybody, I mean,
we're never going to get through the list. Sherry, do you have the actual increases in a spreadsheet that you can get read to us so that we understand the people that were the positions that we're dealing with for these raises?
>> Well, while she's digging that up, can I make a motion? Sure, go ahead. I would make a motion that we
set a 3% salary increase for all
non collective bargaining positions,
Including J tunnel.
I'll second that.
>> So
one correction, you probably want to make. Transfers Employees
that need more than that to make minimum wage once minimum wage jumps again by state law. Is that other
than the transfer station.
>> Correct.
That actually does not affect the transfer station that affects a bunch of library employees, and I think that may affect
some of the registrar.
The
voting positions.
>> I didn't see that in your list, so I apologize.
Well, can you amend that. It's in your list, I would amend
I'll amend the motion to bring all,
everyone to, bring everyone that is not covered under this
up to the state minimum wage.
I'll second.
>> Okay.
So basically, that means that any any employee not covered by a union contract is gonna receive a 3% raise. And then anyone that is that is that gets the 3% raise and does not get to the state minimum wage is going to be boosted to the minimum wage when it occurs. Yes, the exception will be the transfer station. We already agreed we would do something with that. So I'll make a motion to that effect after if you want. Right. That's
different.
So
let's sit there and vote on this unless anybody has any further discussions on this issue.
No? All right. All those in favor?
Aye. Aye.
Okay.
>> I would make a motion that we increase the transfer station
attendance salaries to $18 an hour.
>> All right, and currently the transfers station attendants are at what Sherry?
Hold on one second, please.
Up there around 16.
Yeah.
That's what they are.
Trying to get them closer to the surrounding.
Yeah, I'm with surrounding town.
>> So we're talking,
because you're trying to get them to that rate, it's a 12.5% increase,
>> which they probably deserve for all of the garbage. I'm sorry for And the the fact that they're out in all weather.
>> I was really just thinking about the garbage they deal with. Yep. Okay.
All right. Paula, you got to smile at that. Come on. That's like what I did with Eric this morning. It's
a silent smile, she had her mute on.
Jeff,
it's
household waste products. Yes, Paula
>> has a screen up, Adrian. That's her picture that she has up. So when she's having dinner, it just sits there.
>> Right. I have no, I have my I'm live, live enough I right
>> don't believe that. If you were live, you would have seconded that motion right so we can move on. Okay. So did someone second? Okay.
For the transfer station is 1632.
And so has has not been seconded yet.
>> I thought I seconded it, but maybe maybe you just didn't hear. I said your picture was quiet so I was
was staying very still.
>> I was miming. So Paul a second it, Jeff. Got it. So 18968.
>> All right, so a 10.3%
increase.
And Paula seconded it. So further discussion, no. All those in favor, aye. Aye.
Aye. Jeff Murray did say aye silently, Amanda. He raised his hand. I know. He's good.
Silent.
Alright.
Yes. I have my camera on.
>> Alright.
So we
have covered J. Tuttle
related to
within the first motion.
And then we are at
B potential position changes. Eric, what is that related to?
>> So we've discussed that over the last three or four meetings.
So
you had asked, the board had asked us to bake in
to the budget
a series of potential changes, but you hadn't made any firm decisions on whether you were going to accept them or not. Wanted to see what the effect is on the total budget. And I can kind of list what they are if you would like. Please.
Okay, so one in the land use department increasing the building official,
the shared service from five to seven hours, because I think that lines up basically with what our actual usages.
And number two, either make permanent the increase in the CEOs hours from ten to fifteen a week or add the town planner.
You would ask me for further information
on
wages
and planner information which I provided. Under
the it budget increase the it support from eight to twelve hours a month, I had a discussion again with South Windsor
because although I had broached that subject with them several months ago,
they had just now said they will have the capacity to do that if we so chose.
Would say it so far has been one of our biggest employee complaints,
just the lack of timeliness and it services,
just due to the fact that you know we're we basically have four hours of support every two weeks. So this increases that you
know.
By 50%.
>> What was your what was your first thing I heard the planner the fifteen hours
or add a planner what was the first thing I'm sorry. Land you five to seven hours.
Okay, didn't we already make that change in this current year though?
>> So
right now we've increased
the ZEOs
at least on a temporary basis from ten to fifteen hours a week. Okay.
That's a decision
I don't know that you've made that decision permanently, though.
>> I don't object to it. So you were thinking we're rolling it back?
>> Well,
you tell me, you know, I mean, one option
is to
bring on a planner for X number of hours
or
bring on the CEO
and increase the CEO's hours or do both or neither.
You know those are really the options.
I mean I think you should do one or the other basically,
recommend one or the other.
Both would be even better, but you know again
we have some pretty significant cost constraints, so you may not want to consider that.
>> So the cost difference of the additional hours in the coming budget year would be what?
I don't know if I have that.
>> Did you type it into the spreadsheet? Would you would it go one year to the next? Was already? Yes. Is that baked in? Yeah, you can see it Okay. The
So what's the comparison to last year? I'm sorry, I can't have, I got too many screens open.
Right.
>> Give me a second. What's the line item? What's the number?
Should be building department, I think.
>> So one of them will be building department, which is 807.
The other will be,
the planning and zoning.
>> Wait. Did Scott fall down? Is he alright?
He's fine. He's out looking for something. Oh, okay. I looked up all of a sudden he was gone.
The other one is 817.
>> So go back to this one. $8.00
salary line?
>> Yeah. Correct.
What's the difference, Jeff? Last year, this year? $44,337
Alright. So I mean, I I wouldn't change it. Just approve that one. That's Yeah. I wouldn't change it back. Do we need to do a separate approval for that?
>> No,
I don't. Mean, ultimately, you're going to approve the budget. Those were just things we've discussed,
but as far as I know, you hadn't made any final decision on. Well, yeah.
>> I mean, as far as I'm concerned, I mean That was decided while you were in surgery, Eric. Sorry, we should have greased you. That's okay. That's fine. I don't
have a problem with increasing
the hours on the land use side.
On the planner,
I would sit there and I would push the planner off. Simply Yeah, I would agree.
>> I think at this point we've got too much on our plate.
>> Okay.
Anybody have a problem with the planner Scott I know you will have.
>> I think that we're, we have that's enough for the year, I
would like to see it happen next year.
>> I will support you as long as we don't have another bridge fall over. We're good. The
>> the one thing that I would ask, I did talk to to to Jed
today,
and he he did have a request. If we did not pass the town planner, his request was oriented toward
a
potentially
subcontracting
out
someone to do the zoning regulations on
low income housing or some of the housing issues, Eric, that are going on. I think
>> Jeff Murray had some ideas on that. Did you have a number attached to your ideas, Jeff?
>> No, I didn't, but I think that's the direction we should head in
>> at least this year. I mean, Eric, what do we need? Like 4,000 or 5,000 to get started on that?
>> Know, hard to tell.
Yeah, I mean, 5,000 would put a pretty good dent in it. Alright, so I would make a motion there. One
>> second, Adrian, before you make the motion. Unless
we're anticipating wrapping everything up at this meeting, which I don't necessarily know that we will
or can. I mean, I would like to sit there and see the final number before we do that.
>> Well, final number for what? For a planner? No. For the budget in total.
Well, I mean,
we're not the last say anyways. Board of Finance can take out whatever they want when we're done. Well, that's And we all disagree that we need this. You could, you could always vote no on my motion.
Well, I'm not necessarily saying vote no. I'm saying get a better number. The number is not great, but the number is what it needs to be.
You know, I mean, we're trying to be as frugal as possible here, but also not stay in the dark ages.
I mean, we have made an argument for every single thing that we've put in this budget.
So,
so you're right. $5,000
>> for someone to sit there and review. Well, we can put it in it. We can, we'll ask the Board of Finance to create a fund for $5,000
for zoning or regulation
updating.
And that way it can go if you don't use it all in one year or we don't find somebody,
know, the next year we put more in it if that's what we need to do and we get it done next year. Okay, so what I would suggest is line item 803320,
>> which is the line item for contract planner, which we've used in the past
for specialty,
you know, one year allocations.
>> So is it a fund
or a line item, though? Because it's not a fund, it's a line item. Can we, I'd rather see it in a fund so if we don't use it all, can roll it to the next year. And if we don't get somebody for that amount of money, then we put more in it the following year to finally get somebody.
You know what I mean?
That seem reasonable?
>> So you want to ask the Board of Finance to create a permanent fund
for planning services?
>> Yes.
Does that seem unreasonable before you take a lot of notes?
>> No, it's not unreasonable.
If that's how you want to do it, that's how I mean, ultimately it's a Board of Finance's decision whether they want to do that, but whether you do it as a permanent standalone fund or whether you do that as a line item is strictly up to you.
>> I'm just worried that you in the past have said that we have a hard time getting people to work on smaller projects sometimes,
and that maybe they won't bite because we don't have the right amount of money or the big enough project. And we may have to fund this a piecemeal until we get to a big enough thing, you know?
That's my impetus.
All right, make that motion because I don't have a problem with it. Okay. I would make a motion that we ask the Board of Finance to add $5,000
to a
fund for planning services.
I'll second.
>> All right. Further discussion,
Paula, Jeff, Scott.
Scott, since you're in the zoning area and you're always involved with that, what's your feeling related to that? Anything is better than nothing.
Okay.
Alright. Well, then let's move on. All those in favor, aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Okay.
We're good. Did we
I take out the planner. Correct?
>> Take out the planner. Correct. Okay.
I would make motion that we increase building official services from five to seven hours
and that we increase the IT budget from,
what do we, at five hours a month to eight? Is that what you're looking for? Eight to We're going from eight to twelve a month. Eight hours to twelve hours per month. God,
>> eight hours to twelve hours. Why don't you go eight Also
permanently
put the land use hours at fifteen.
>> Fine.
Also permanently amended to accept the amendment to change the land use hours from ten to 15 permanently.
>> Eric, on the IT side, realistically,
how many hours do we need?
Like really need? Forget what you're going to get. What would you like to have?
>> You know,
the long and the short of it is,
To
me, the difference is in the timeliness
of response.
The more hours you have, the quicker we can get to stuff.
Mean everything gets done eventually.
Do you still
>> can you answer the question? Do you need four hours a week?
>> I mean,
hours a week would be better than four hours every two weeks.
I mean, I'd I'd love to go to four hours a week, but I mean, you know, I'd like support in a lot of areas. With this change, you're basically looking at three hours per week.
>> If we go by what's what we're what we've talked about,
your eight to twelve.
>> Well,
no.
Twelve hours a month. Yeah, three hours a week, yes.
>> Give or take.
Is that how they're allotting it to you or are they allotting you two differently?
>> No, so normally what we're doing is we're doing a four hour block every two weeks.
And the reality
is it takes,
you know, when David's on-site, takes a certain amount of time. You know, if you're initializing a computer or whatever you're doing,
takes a discrete block to do it. We've kind of settled on that as the most efficient way.
>> So, this is getting you 50% more than you have right now? Correct.
>> All right. Let's use it as a launching pad next Go
ahead. Make your motion.
>> Well, the motion's already in place. So it's increase IT from eight to twelve,
make building official hours permit from ten to fifteen hours, going from ten to fifteen hours as a permanent change
and increase the official shared services building official from five to seven hours.
Someone want to second that.
I'll
second.
>> Okay. Further discussion on those three points?
Anybody have any problems with any of them?
Okay. All those in favor, aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye.
I love the delay. The delay is just the best part about the list. It's very strange.
Yeah, no, it's perfect. All right.
Right, Adrian, what do you have next on your list?
>> Well, let's take them piecemeal because I don't know what's going to be
upsetting or not upsetting. So I would want to see the promotion, which we already talked about, of Richard Biggins from Maintainer one to Maintainer two. That would be my first motion.
He's already doing this. He's already qualified. He's basically doing it, so.
And he already worked for the Let's Dell
>> go back to the, this was probably either before Eric.
Didn't we discuss this and you're just saying we haven't voted on it? I know we've discussed it, but we haven't made it official. We did not Then vote
make the motion. I just did. Just did. Somebody second it.
I'll second it.
I'll second it, Amanda. All those in favor?
Aye. Aye.
And
the delay.
It's fine. That's good. It
>> makes me smile, Jeff. Paula's got to pull his hand.
All
right.
>> All right.
My next motion for public works would be to
institute bringing in a
full
time summer helper.
And again, we've discussed this. We've discussed, but we haven't, we have not accepted it. All right. And the total cost related to the summer help, just so everybody's aware? We're under 20, right? 20,000.
20. Even.
>> Did
someone second that? Did Polly second that? I'll second. Yep. Okay. All those Do
>> we need discussion?
We've discussed it already. Okay. Just wanna make sure. I don't wanna feel like anybody All got left those in favor? Aye.
Aye.
Now he's doing it on purpose.
>> Nice
work.
You are delaying this meeting for.
Go ahead, Adrian. Next.
>> Add
an additional maintainer
one to the staff at public works full time.
Okay. And Sherry, the total cost of this?
Well, somebody second it.
I'll second. Alright. Sherry, cost of that.
Salaries at 60,000
and insurance is $27.06.
I don't think the salary is 60,000.
>> It's less than that for a maintainer one. It's maintainer one. So it's one step down.
Well.
That's the amount I put in, so.
>> Hang on. I'd I'd give you that in a sec.
>> Let's just make a note that we address that though before we send that to Board of Finance that the number in there is correct, please. Yep.
Thank you.
Well, we have voted yet. What is the number?
>> No, I'm just saying if it passes.
Give or take your total, it's what
64,
>> isn't it? Something like? So, the salary would be $47,600
much for a
maintainer one.
medical?
>> And how much? Wait a second. Wait.
What's the hourly rate, Eric, on the contract? So, the hourly rate.
22. The new rate will be $22.88.
>> Oh, but I think she,
but she has, but she has town FICA probably rolled in.
>> Well, this is new
new rate is 22.88
an hour.
>> It's on our spreadsheet. So it so at forty hours,
it's it's $47,590
And then I'm sure there'll be some overtime which is accounted for in a different line item. Line item? Correct.
So it's $47,590.40
>> Okay, So plus benefits. So maybe she was adding benefits to the total. That's what I'm thinking that I think your your number, Sherry, probably has Murph and
>> Yeah. Murph FICA rolled in. They do. Yeah. Where the difference is.
18 for the record that. Yes.
The full up cost for maintainer one,
you know, is $70,938
>> Okay. All
right. So did someone second that,
Paula? Yes. Further discussion?
Just so we
as a board are
making this decision really kind of limits us in a lot of other areas. So if we're all in favor
of
pushing forward with
public works and giving public works more people,
you know, it's going to limit us in doing other things potentially.
So just everybody needs to be aware of that as we vote on this. I just,
>> my my only comments I agree with you and my only comment, though, is that if we are going to try to maintain our costs
as we start to do
more roadwork,
the easiest way to do that is to have staff in house
that can complete more of the work that we would otherwise need to subcontract, whether it's basement replacement,
drainage work,
drainage prep,
backfilling on a on a road that's been paved
you know all of those things, but you know.
Money and if we don't do them in house we pay someone else to do them, and that is
genuinely more expensive
period
so that's my
that's my spiel.
Okay.
Anyone
else.
I agree with Eric's I mean Adrian's position.
Okay.
All right. All those in favor?
Aye.
Aye. All
right.
Let's go to
>> the next issue, Adrian, on the list. Yep. So the next I've got that we had still hanging
is
administrator's
office increased to admin position hours.
>> Okay.
Are we going to make a motion to do that? Or is this one of those items that were kind of I'll
>> make a motion so we can go into discussion. Motion
to increase the hours on the position
to full time?
Thirty four hours.
Thirty
four hours? Yes.
>> Okay.
And what's the total increase if we do that, Sherry?
How much is it gonna cost? Yeah.
>> 18,021
is on the spreadsheet.
Okay. Because the increase is 39,391.
>> Okay. That's salary alone. Remember, Just there's also significant
benefit
>> salary alone. And then
there'll be an insurance
increase too.
And MRF.
21,000
and then MRF.
At 18%.
So somewhere in the range of 42 to 43,000,
>> Eric. Is that about right? That is about right. That is about right. Yep.
Okay.
>> Do we have a second so we can get into discussion? Yes, I second.
I'm sorry. I apologize. I spawned in here.
I thought you seconded it too, Paul. Thank you, Jeff. I saw Jeff's hand go up, I never heard it.
My hand?
No, the other Jeff. The delayed Paul. All
>> right, so,
you
know, where I stand on this is I
would love to see this occur, but I also sit there and look at this and going, if we're going to make all these other decisions, it's probably one of the items that we're going to have to potentially delay.
We're probably somewhere
north of 300,000
to $400,000
in total increases across the town budget
right now.
We've got to pick what we think are the most important
priorities.
So if public works is the most important priority, then we're going to have to have some things not
move forward.
So that's just me.
>> Well, Jeff, our complaint number and
concern this year that I've heard overwhelmingly is the roadwork, and I think we're Yeah,
Yeah, that's mine too. And unfortunately,
>> you know how the budgets go, we
can only absorb so much in
one year that I think the public will swallow as far as an increase.
>> Okay.
Well,
let's get on the record as to what we're trying to do.
>> All those in favor? Well, can we back up? Are we still? We're in a hurry.
Paula?
>> No, I'm just reading what Eric said. Yeah, mean, that's what I was doing. I was gonna ask a couple of questions around that, but if we're not.
>> Well, if you'd like to, you go ahead. I give everybody fair
opportunity to question ask questions or get information.
Eric,
>> we asked you to give us a list of the things that would be additional.
I see all the list of things she's doing
Under current roles and responsibilities
and
you said that.
Additional things that you want her to do did I miss something or is it just the three items at the bottom.
>> No, those are, I mean, those are the biggest three for me.
I mean, the reality is, you know, I use Amanda's kind of an all purpose
to fill in everywhere.
She actually doesn't do all that much in terms of
assist me directly.
And that's for two reasons. One,
she's there less than half the number of work hours I am in the week. So most of the time when I need something, there's nobody there anyway.
You know, and secondly,
you know, there's enough on her plate.
You know, and the reason it's on her plate is because as a board, you've made a decision that you wanted to really emphasize
communication.
>> No, I get that. Mean, I can read the document that you put in your pocket that's available to us on the public. Point is,
I just want to understand what you're saying free up your time by transitioning some of your
administrative work to her exactly what you're thinking.
Like for instance, you mentioned the VOIP.
I would be concerned that
I don't know that Amanda has a background in the technical side of VOIP, which is was is a big part of that, isn't it?
No.
Yes,
but neither do I.
>> Oh, okay. I you blocked your voice for fairly well then because I I thought you actually
grasped it pretty well.
>> I mean, I know what I want.
You
know, yeah.
>> You know, I attended that meeting
and, you know, there was some open ended questions.
I got a few of the answers and Amanda was just gathering up that information and sending it on to the vendor.
And I think we're pretty much wrapped up with that mostly.
>> Yeah, look, I'm just saying that that's a kind of a thing that
I look at as an example.
And that's something that
basically
I did most of the legwork on start to finish,
But that's something I would have happily pawned off on somebody else if I could have.
All
>> right, so so as
you know, this is not the easiest one of us the one to vote on. So,
simply, we need to sit there and do that. So let's just call vote on it. So all those in favor?
The dog is in favor.
>> She's very much in favor. The coyotes are out. All those opposed?
>> Okay.
All All those that abstain?
And I'm going to say why I'm saying. I was saying because No, I'm no, actually no. The rest of us do not need to hear why you're abstaining. I'm going tell you anyways.
>> My idea is personally that I would rather put something in the budget and if Board of Finance or the town as a whole feels that it's not appropriate
and we've made a valid argument for it to let them say no.
You know, we we know that we need this, but you know, we keep stalling on it. That's, that's my only take on it. I would rather let the town say I don't want better communication. I don't want
our town administrator to have more help
>> than us do it. I think we're all in agreement that it's
>> it's just we want Eric to be more productive, right? So, I know. I I just feel like we're struggling on this one and I and honestly, I know the place sucks. Listen, Adrian, you're not wrong. I mean, that position should
>> we should do a lot in this town, but I know. And I know what It's getting it is through to
the financial realities of where we're at and what is occurring. So
>> it's I guess I am more optimistic that the town as a whole
realizes
that we are
we've been lacking,
you know, and I but that's my only take maybe I'm for once I'm the optimist in the room so I'll take that moment because that's not your only me so.
So a taxed and tax and spend republican.
>> No, I think a conservative Republican that realizes that we've been too conservative for too long and now we're paying for it. Okay.
>> All right. So I I'm I'm
no, I don't think any one of us is going to debate that issue. I think it's just a situation where I think we're in for a heavy lift with this budget. Think there's I a lot of don't disagree with that And
at
I do believe that they're all positive things for the community. And to be really honest, we should do them all. But
I think in certain cases, we're gonna have to pick and choose. I think if we're defending every one of them,
we're
gonna be We're being honest. I know. But
>> it's hard either way. And to add to Adrian's comments, I mean, we have to wait all these additions that we're doing. And like I drive up, coming home on Hendi Road and the road is actually falling off on their side,
>> mean, those are things we have to keep our roads up. I'm sorry, but we have to put some money into their I road get it, but as we start to do more roadwork eventually, that's going to put more pressure on Eric to be,
you know,
double checking public works and Jay and
helping try to find I mean to eric's credit, you know we were able to get some some grant money, you know, to be able to do some of the paving you know those things happened because Eric had time to do it so
again.
Votes done I get it so I'll let it go I'm sorry.
It's okay.
All right.
>> What other main issues do we have to address before I exit this meeting?
Okay.
>> I think the last thing is really a review of the capital fund allocations
and make sure that you're all on board with what I recommended
for capital fund allocations.
>> I don't believe any of us brought up anything as far as changes to that.
Okay.
>> Well,
let's I mean, I was reviewing it before the meeting. I mean, it's really not that.
So
public works capital equipment
proposal for this year's 110.
Oh, no, sorry, 01/2015.
Yeah.
>> Okay. And Jeff, that is largely driven by the fact that when,
you know, we're looking at
some really steep increases in equipment costs right now. To put it in perspective, in 2019,
we bought a Peterbilt
plow truck.
It was $192,000
delivered.
That same truck identically spec'd right now is $2.65.
So there's been over a 30% increase
just in that one item
in four years. So we're faced with some pretty significant headwind in that category.
Yes.
So
>> I don't yeah. I don't think we have anything else budget wise to review. Thank god
we thank god this board bought that Peterbilt truck in 2019. Right? Well, we're buying and we're gonna ask to buy another one, but we're gonna buy a freightliner because it's literally $30,000
cheaper.
>> So let's just go through the proposed. So the fire engine fund proposal is a $100,000.
Right.
You know, my question on that one, and I know you had something in there. And last year, we put in 60,000. And the current balance is 40.
Why is that? Because we're buying supplies?
>> Yeah,
that balance should be
close to zero. Capital
fund allocations a couple months late, they finally got the washer dryer.
So they wiped out the majority of that. Okay.
>> Alright.
Building maintenance $60,000
that should be higher.
Bunker Hill Bridge replacement 120.
So that leaves us that will get us to $400,000
or pretty close. Right within a couple thousand. Which is our number that we need to sit there and do that construction project.
>> No, that's no, it's delaying
once.
And we're going to spend at least that much on the follow on year.
Unless
we can get ourselves
that
the reason why I didn't want to increase that to what the actual value should be right now is because I think there's a reasonable chance
the federal reg change is going to
going to allow us a greater contribution
from the federal government,
but we just don't have the state guidelines on that yet. So, I'm actually hoping the cost of the Bunker Hill Bridge replacement
goes down a little bit, but
but
>> I can't guarantee it. Yeah, I mean, and right now we're still in design phase, so we're okay. We don't. When do we have to have the money in place?
>> Realistically,
a year and a half from now.
Oh. Excuse me. So we got two more budget cycles to fund it, this one and the next one. Alright.
>> And when are we getting done? I thought you said the project was started April
2023,
2022?
>> Well,
it's not gonna be 2022.
You know, considering where they're at now, I don't think it'll be 2023
either. I think we're looking at start of construction in 2024.
>> Oh yeah.
We hope we don't have any more plugs.
>> Not what
I heard at the last meeting, Eric. Well,
>> I mean they said optimistic.
If you look at the actual timetables,
you know, they're talking about construction spring twenty twenty four.
The
engineer says he thinks there's still some possibility
of a 2023
construction
season,
but
there's no, that's not in the timeline right now. So, the follow on bridge designer
would have to step up their game and exceed their milestones to do that
is how I would put it.
>> All right, well as long as we're not required to have all of the funding up this year before they get started, that would be my big concern. So
if that's not the case, then I have no problem with it. Yeah,
we're slowly building to where we need to be. All right. So the Bridge and Culvert Fund is $100,000
with a current balance of 127,000
That's not enough.
The Tree Fund is $75,000
with $18,000
in the fund currently. That's not enough.
Roadwork fund is proposal of $3.30 with 150,000
currently in the fund, that's not enough.
Town Aid Road gets us 193,000
with a current balance of 95.
Reval is a standard 16500
and
plan of conservation and development
fund is $5,000
So those are all the capital
fund allocations. I don't have any problems with any of those. Does anybody want to increase or decrease any of those line items?
>> I don't think we can afford to even though we need to.
>> I mean, we need to go up, but does anyone want to decrease?
>> No, God, that'd be the worst thing we could do.
>> Okay. So do we want to approve that? Do we need to approve that?
>> I mean, the one thing I could throw out there is do we
need the 16 and change considering we just did a revower? Is that money we need to put aside for,
excuse me, for for legal?
>> There's only $10,520
left from the last reval, which means we put in basically that much each year and they he has Oh, I understand that. I'm just
just asking.
>> Well, we're better off I was trying to find you a nickel in a haystack. If we're better off to to to,
save for those types of projects anyway because we'll never get it all upfront in one year anyway. So I have no problem with that. Do we want to have Sherry finalize the sheet and then we'll just vote on that final number after the fact? Yes.
>> The point.
Unless we have something else on the thing.
>> I was gonna suggest just that what I was gonna do is update the salary spreadsheet that
you currently have to reflect
the changes
and then also
update the overall budget to come to a bottom line percentage.
And when I'm finished
with that, I go over it with Eric,
then we'll send
out a copy to each of you. Okay.
Alright. Adrian, if you could, could you handle correspondence
>> and public speak for me? So I have one further thing that's not represented
on the funds,
and that is one of the recommendations I had is that we consider setting up a senior transportation
fund.
We've been lucky the last two cycles and that we've been able to get
our vehicles funded by federal grants,
but that's not always going to be the case.
Know, those grants are
somewhat difficult to get.
I think we ought to set aside us some funds yearly
for senior transportation
and vehicle replacement.
>> I can, but we don't really have the funds right now to do that this year.
If we don't, we don't.
>> I would sit there and tell you I
believe
our our our
tremendous senior coordinator Cathy Plazi got us a a grant for a vehicle this this time around. Is that correct, Eric? That is She's very
done it like the last three times around. Thank you so much, Kathy, which greatly appreciated. So maybe in the next budget cycle, we worry about putting money away for that. All right. Fair enough. So you're off, Jeff. Well, I'll go Jeff, with
>> before you
run,
we don't have another meeting scheduled. Do we wanna try and do that now? Or are we gonna do that through email?
>> We can schedule it from Mondays are always better for me.
So do you wanna do next Monday? Quick.
I mean, gives it time to get to the board of finance. Correct?
Mhmm.
>> Adrian, do you have a problem with that date?
I do not. You're looking you're looking like it's
What's the date?
The twenty eighth.
Twenty eighth. Okay. Can you do that? Yeah.
>> Worst worst case, I'll call in.
Diane will have to deal with me not having a camera at that day.
>> She can she can live with it. Alright. Okay. Thank you very much everybody. Bye bye. Bye, Jeff. Thank you. Bye.
There's Jeff.
Alright.
Public
comment, Kathy Palazzi.
>> Thank you for the compliment. Always appreciated.
Love my job. I know it's a voluntary job. It's the best job I ever had.
Love it.
>> Thank you. You're doing a great job, guys. Keep it up. Thank you. Thank you, Kathy. Keep it up.
Victoria?
I'm all set. I was late to the party.
>> Well,
luckily it is recorded, Victoria, so you'll be able to catch it again.
Joan Hebert.
All set. Thank you.
I'm sorry. I said Joan. Joanne,
I apologize.
That's okay.
If
that is it, then motion to adjourn.
>> Great, Dan, you missed Diane, Granny or Diane. Both Diane. I
can't see any of those people.
>> Why are they not showing up on my thing? Granny, you're not. Do you have anything to say?
>> Oh, I I'm all set. Thank you. Good to see all your faces. And Diane Choquette, do you still have a camera?
>> Oh, she doesn't have a camera on. Okay.
That's ironic.
That is really ironic, Diane, Grenier.
Diane, you had nothing?
Thank you, Mr. You
got to see me in my jammies.
>> Diane ChoCat, you're all set. The only question I have is
We don't have questions. For you guys to I do have a question. Comments only.
The
community center.
>> We all dress it at the last meeting. Okay, thanks. We still have to vote on total.
Okay.
Alright.
Was what was the question.
>> How we are if we are going to fund it this year, how we are going to fund it because there's been talk about
using the
American cares act money for that.
So we would put that in the budget, so it goes through as a budget a piece of the budget.
And that way it's done
and it gives the Community a chance to have input.
Rather than us just making a decision, I mean we have purview on the funds, but asking the Community for permission, I think, is the best way to go so.
That's what we're kind of moving towards.
Fair enough.
Paula, can you second?
I'll second.
>> All right. All in favor of motion to adjourn?
Aye.
We
are four-zero
and Jeff is absent.
Thank you everyone.
Thank you. All right, thank
you. Cheers.